<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<study api_version="0.6">
  <id>2501</id>
  <name>Mouse model to quantify genotype-epigenotype variations_RNA</name>
  <active>true</active>
  <user_id>191</user_id>
  <managers>
    <manager>
      <login>ncb</login>
      <email>ncb@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Nathalie C Smerdon</name>
      <id>191</id>
    </manager>
  </managers>
  <owners>
    <owner>
      <login>ms27</login>
      <email>ms27@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Marcela Sjoberg</name>
      <id>711</id>
    </owner>
  </owners>
  <!-- Family has been deprecated -->
  <family_id></family_id>
  <created_at>2013-01-16 13:54:59 +0000</created_at>
  <updated_at>2013-01-30 11:22:33 +0000</updated_at>
  <descriptors>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study description</name>
      <value>In order to examine the impact of genetic variation on epigenetic marking and control of gene expression, this study has been initiated using two inbred strains of mice, C57BL/6J and CAST/Eij which genomes indicate substantial structural and nucleotide variation.  Stocks of adult C57BL/6J and CAST/Eij mice as well as CAST/BL6 and BL6/CAST reciprocal hybrids are employed for isolation of pure and synchronous populations of B and T-lymphocytes. RNA-Seq expression analysis will be performed in total RNA extracted from B-lymphocytes isolated from males and females of both strains and hybrids.
 
This data is part of a pre-publication release. For information on the proper use of pre-publication data shared by the Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute (including details of any publication moratoria), please see http://www.sanger.ac.uk/datasharing/
</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Does this study contain samples that are contaminated with human DNA which must be removed prior to analysis?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Does this study require the removal of X chromosome and autosome sequence?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Does this study require y chromosome data to be separated from x and autosomal data before archival?</name>
      <value>false</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ENA Project ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Abstract</name>
      <value>Epigenetic mechanisms including non-coding RNAs are involved in the acquisition and maintenance of specific gene expression programmes during development and differentiation. Examining the extent to which DNA structural variation correlates with epigenomic and transcriptional changes is important to identify the basis of disease development, quantitative variation, adaptation and evolution. With the aim of identifying genotype-mediated epigenotype variations that account for transcriptional changes, we have used two inbred strains of mice, C57BL/6J and CAST/Eij as a model.
Pure synchronous populations of B and T-lymphocytes were isolated from males and females of both strains and reciprocal hybrids and total RNA was extracted for each sample in duplicates. Total RNA expression analysis will be performed: (1) to inspect in B lymphocytes of each strain the transcriptional programme that maintain the cellular phenotype; (2) to inspect in B lymphocytes of each strain the transcriptional programme that supress proliferation and apoptosis; (3) to look at the differential expression of various species of RNA (coding and non-coding) as a consequence of genomic variation; (3) to determine parental origin and cis/trans strain-specific effects based on the reciprocal hybrids RNA-Seq analysis.

</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Title</name>
      <value>Mouse model to quantify genotype-epigenotype variations     </value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ENA Study Accession Number</name>
      <value>ERP002223</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study Visibility</name>
      <value>Public</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Do any of the samples in this study contain human DNA?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Are all the samples to be used in this study commercially available, unlinked anonymised cell-lines?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study name abbreviation</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What is the data release strategy for this study?</name>
      <value>open</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Will you be using WTSI's standard access agreement?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>How is the data release to be timed?</name>
      <value>delayed</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Reason for delaying release</name>
      <value>assay of no other use</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Delay for</name>
      <value>12 months</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Alignments in BAM</name>
      <value>true</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Please explain the reason for delaying release</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Comment regarding data release timing and approval</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Policy Url</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Policy title</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>EGA DAC Accession Number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>EGA Policy Accession Number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ArrayExpress Accession Number</name>
      <value>E-ERAD-155</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Has the delay period been approved by the data sharing committee for this project?</name>
      <value>Yes</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What is the reason for preventing data release?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Has this been approved?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Comment regarding prevention of data release and approval</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Data access group</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>SNP study ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>SNP parent study ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Number of gigabases per sample (minimum 0.15)</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>HMDMC approval number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study Type</name>
      <value>Transcriptome Analysis</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What sort of study is this?</name>
      <value>transcriptomics</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Reference Genome</name>
      <value>Mus_musculus (GRCm38)</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Faculty Sponsor</name>
      <value>David Adams</value>
    </descriptor>
  </descriptors>
</study>
