<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<study api_version="0.6">
  <id>391</id>
  <name>500 Exome</name>
  <active>true</active>
  <user_id>93</user_id>
  <followers>
    <follower>
      <login>ekh</login>
      <email>ekh@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Eleanor Howard</name>
      <id>128</id>
    </follower>
    <follower>
      <login>fp1</login>
      <email>fp1@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Felicity Payne</name>
      <id>183</id>
    </follower>
    <follower>
      <login>jillian</login>
      <email>jillian@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Jillian L Durham</name>
      <id>173</id>
    </follower>
  </followers>
  <managers>
    <manager>
      <login>ajc</login>
      <email>ajc@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Alison J Coffey</name>
      <id>129</id>
    </manager>
    <manager>
      <login>dw2</login>
      <email>dw2@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Danielle Walker</name>
      <id>86</id>
    </manager>
  </managers>
  <owners>
    <owner>
      <login>ajc</login>
      <email>ajc@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Alison J Coffey</name>
      <id>129</id>
    </owner>
  </owners>
  <!-- Family has been deprecated -->
  <family_id></family_id>
  <created_at>2009-10-30 10:12:17 +0000</created_at>
  <updated_at>2011-02-23 16:01:25 +0000</updated_at>
  <descriptors>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Delay for</name>
      <value>12 months</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study description</name>
      <value>Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have identified a large number of common variants associated with complex human phenotypes. However in all cases the proportion of the trait variance explained by common variants remains small (less than 5%) suggesting that additional variants contributing to disease and trait heritability have yet to be discovered. One hypothesis is that rarer variants (which are poorly tagged in current GWA arrays) maybe more penetrant than common variants and collectively contribute to a substantial proportion of trait variance.  Indeed, such variants, mostly described within exons and affecting protein sequence, have already been found to influence metabolic traits such as lipid levels. 



This project is a pilot study focused on re-sequencing the entire exome in DNA samples from 500 individuals with the aim of exploring the technical feasibility of this approach and identifying coding variants that are associated with a propensity to develop metabolic abnormalities (defined primarily through elevated glucose levels/diagnosis of type 2 diabetes mellitus [T2DM]) among overweight and obese individuals. The samples are from an extreme discordant case-control study nested within the clinically well-characterized CoLaus population-based study of around 6,000 participants from Lausanne, Switzerland. 

</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Will you be using WTSI's standard access agreement?</name>
      <value>Yes</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study Visibility</name>
      <value>Hold</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Comment regarding data release timing and approval</name>
      <value>The RCA states that the data are not to be released to the EGA until after the publication is put together. Any change to this would need to be reviewed by the GSK lawyers. DSC approval 12.10.10 - Carol Scott and Sarah Hunt will do release.</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Reason for delaying release</name>
      <value>other</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Has this been approved?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>EGA DAC Accession Number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Number of gigabases per sample (minimum 0.15)</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>SNP parent study ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>SNP study ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ENA Study Accession Number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Are all the samples to be used in this study commercially available, unlinked anonymised cell-lines?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Policy</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Please explain the reason for delaying release (e.g., pre-existing collaborative agreement)</name>
      <value>The RCA states that the data are not to be released to the EGA until after the publication is put together. Any change to this would need to be reviewed by the GSK lawyers. DSC approval 12.10.10 - Carol Scott and Sarah Hunt will do release.</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>How is the data release to be timed?</name>
      <value>delayed</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Do any of the samples in this study contain human DNA?</name>
      <value>Yes</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ENA Project ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ArrayExpress Accession Number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Has the delay period been approved by the data sharing committee for this project?</name>
      <value>Yes</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Title</name>
      <value>TO BE PROVIDED</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Comment regarding prevention of data release and approval</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>EGA Policy Accession Number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Does this study contain samples that are contaminated with human DNA which must be removed prior to analysis?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What is the reason for preventing data release?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Alignments in BAM</name>
      <value>true</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What is the data release strategy for this study?</name>
      <value>managed</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study name abbreviation</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Abstract</name>
      <value>The 500 exome pilot project is a collaborative exome resequencing experiment using 500 individuals from the CoLaus study based in Lausanne, Switzerland. The collaboration is between the Sanger Institute, GSK and Lausanne University. CoLaus  is a population-based study of around 6,000 participants from Lausanne. The case samples for this pilot have been chosen to have a BMI&gt;25 and diabetes or high blood glucose levels, and are 1:1 matched with controls. The controls have low glucose levels and are matched to the cases for BMI (within 1 unit), age (within 7 years) and sex.  



Sequence capture will be performed on individual samples using the Agilent Sure Select All Exon Kit based on the CCDS database at NCBI. One lane of 54bp read length PE sequencing will be run on an Illumina GAII to assess the quality of the library before requesting additional lanes on a sample by sample basis if required depending on coverage.  Sequence analysis will comprise sequence assembly, sequence mapping to the exome, identification of all variants, mapping variants with respect to exons, noting their likely effect on protein sequence, and capturing the minor allele frequency of each variant identified.



We aim to identify rare genetic variants and eQTLs associated with a propensity to develop metabolic abnormalities among overweight and obese individuals.

</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Reference Genome</name>
      <value>Homo_sapiens (GRCh37_53)</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What sort of study is this?</name>
      <value>genomic sequencing</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study Type</name>
      <value>Exome Sequencing</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Faculty Sponsor</name>
      <value>Ines Barroso</value>
    </descriptor>
  </descriptors>
</study>
